Inventory of the James Barron Hope Papers (I) 1790-1965
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Newspaper and Periodical articles written by or concerning James Barron Hope, 1857-1939. (Box-folder 5:1-22)
  A group of interesting and valuable newspaper clippings and articles in periodicals which are written by, or concern, James Barron Hope.
  - Poem read at Jamestown, Virginia, by James Barron Hope printed in the Baltimore Sun, [May 1857]. (Box-folder 5:1)
    Poem - In May 1857, the two hundredth and fiftieth Anniversary at the settlement of Jamestown.... printed in the Baltimore Sun for 1 June 1902.
  - Letter to the Editor of the Williamsburg Gazette by Benjamin S. Ewell, College of William and Mary, 12 September 1885. (Box-folder 5:2)
    Letter concerns address by W. S. Bogart to Georgia Historical Society on The Four Randolphs of Virginia.
  - Letter of Capt. James Barron Hope declining the use of his name for Congress, 12 July 1880. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - First page of the Norfolk Landmark, James Barron Hope, Editor, 31 July 1880. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Conscience behind the Footlights, 15 February 1885. (Box-folder 5:5)
    Endorsed: "Papa's Editorial" and "Editorial of James Barron Hope."
  - Quotation from Mr. Hope's Lecture, according to the Richmond State,n.d., 3 copies. NCl. (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Article on A Great Writer, James Barron Hope the Virginia Poet, which appeared in The State, 9 March 1891. (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Obituary notice of the death of James Barron Hope Marr, son of Col. R. A. and Jane Barron Hope Marr, in a Norfolk newspaper, January 1894. (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Announcement of the Founders' Day Observance at Jamestown Island, to be held on the next day; from the Richmond [?], 12 May 1895. (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Account of the Celebration of the Settlement of Jamestown, by William and Mary College and the APVA; from the Richmond Times, 14 May 1895. (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning James Barron Hope, n.d., 34 items. NCl. (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Notice of the publication of A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves, a collection of the poems of James Barron Hope, published posthumously by his daughter, Janey Hope Marr, n.d. (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Printed announcement and clipping from the Petersburg Index-Appeal, concerning "Stories and Papers" by Janey Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 5:13)
  - An article on Williamsburg....This ancient city of Virginia, by Rev. Alexander Oberby, n.d. (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Article from the Knoxville Sentinel on Hope's Landmark, [4 January] 1912. (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Lead editorial on James Barron Hope, from the Portsmouth Star,24 March 1924. (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Article on The Confederate Veterans, by Rev. W. H. T. Squires, illustrated with a photograph of James Barron Hope, 1 December 1938. (Box-folder 5:17)
  - Poem, The Nineth of June by Edwards Gregory, written for the Petersburg Index-Appeal,n.d. (Box-folder 5:18)
  - Issue of The Cadet, published by VMI which includes Memorial Poem by Capt. James Barron Hope, with "notes and corrections by J[ames] B[arron] H[ope]," May 1871. (Box-folder 5:19)
  - " The Monthly Visitor, Norfolk, Virginia, Vol. II, No. 4, Vol. III, No. 1, 2," May-September 1872., 3 copies. PV. (Box-folder 5:20)
  - Our School Laureate, Norfolk, Virginia, Vol. 1, No. 5, December 1876. (Box-folder 5:21)
  - The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, Vol. XLVII, No. 4, October 1939. (Box-folder 5:22)
    Includes printed letters from James Barron Hope to Comm. Samuel Barron, 29 April 1861, and James Barron Hope to Miss Imogene Barron, 12 August 1865.
  Series 5: Compositions and Other Literary Materials
- Compositions and Other Literary Materials, 1879-1932, n.d. (Box-folder 6:1-17)
  This collection of manuscript poems, addresses, one story, one sketch and a daguerreotype augment the material found in Series 3, Literary and Artistic Work of James Barron Hope.
  - Poem - Dreamers[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Poem - Alas! He's cold![by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Poem - Let there be Light,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Poem - Three names,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 27 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Poem [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 2 copies, first copy 44 pages on 32 sheets; second copy 42 sheets. ADr. (Box-folder 6:5)
    This poem was probably the Yorktown Ode delivered by James Barron Hope on the 100th anniversary of the surrender of Cornwallis at Yorktown, 19 October 1881.
  - An address [by James Barron Hope] made [Yorktown], October 1879., 35 sheets. ADr. (Box-folder 6:6)
    Includes references to 250th anniversary of Settlement of Jamestown which took place 22 years before this occasion.
  - An address [by James Barron Hope] to Young Gentlemen of Onancock Academy,n.d., 30 sheets. ADr. (Box-folder 6:7)
  - An address [by James Barron Hope] on agriculture, n.d., 29 sheets. ADr. (Box-folder 6:8)
    Includes details of the operation of "Mount Vernon" Plantation.
  - Autograph poems [by James Barron Hope] and some newspaper clippings of poems which are pasted on black pages, December 1860., 30 sheets. AV. (Box-folder 6:9)
  - The Beginning of the End, a story without a plot, n.d., 285 pages. AV. (Box-folder 6:10)
    Cover signature "James Barron Hope."
    Enclosure see item list below, Box-folder 6:10.
  - Enclosed in the AV., sheet of titles of XIX chapters. n.d., 4 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 6:10)
    Enclosed in the above story, Box-folder 6:10.
  - Memoriae Sacrum. Alexander Galt, the Sculptor, by James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 6:11)
    Poem from the South Atlantic.
  - Memorial poem to James Barron Hope by William E. Cameron, Petersburg, Virginia, 20 October 1887. (Box-folder 6:12)
  - A portion of the front page of the Daily Advertiser of Boston, 18 June 1881. (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Account of "James Barron's life in Dictionary of American Biography" in the Virginian Pilot and Norfolk Landmark, 20 June 1932. (Box-folder 6:14)
    Clipping of the same article.
  - Part of the Norfolk Virginian Pilot with article on James Barron Hope, 28 October 1937. (Box-folder 6:15)
  - A daguerreotype of a young man [James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 6:16)
  - Sketch entitled Two Envious Confederates, framed [by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 6:17)
  Series 6: Items given by the granddaughter of James Barron Hope
- Items given by the granddaughter of James Barron Hope, 1790-1964. (Box-folder 7A:1-19)
  These letters, notes and newspaper clippings which were presented by Miss Anne W. Marr, daughter of Mrs. Jane Hope Marr, throw additional light on the life and accomplishments of James Barron Hope.
  - Letter to the donor, 15 September 1964. (Box-folder 7A:1)
  - Agreement of Miles King with Samuel and James Barron, 7 June 1790., 2 items. ADS. (Box-folder 7A:2)
    Agreement to build a new schooner in exchange for land in "little England" on the Hampton River.
  - Invitation to the funeral of Mrs. Elizabeth Mosely Barron, consort of Comm. James Barron, 3 July 1823. (Box-folder 7A:3)
  - Jane A. Hope, Hampton, Virginia, to Caroline M. Campbell, Baltimore, Maryland. Personal letters which tell of the visit of the Frigate "Columbia" to Hampton and the growth of the town. April-December 1854., 5 items. ads. (Box-folder 7A:4)
  - Jane A. Hope, Hampton, Virginia, to Caroline M. Campbell, Baltimore, Maryland, January-November 1855., 7 items. ads. (Box-folder 7A:5)
    References to fear of the fever, to her son James, and to a visit from Captain Barron and his family.
  - Jane A. Hope, Hampton, Virginia, to Caroline [M. Campbell], Baltimore, [Maryland], February-October 1856., 4 items. ads. (Box-folder 7A:6)
    Personal letters with a note in the last, "The people here are very anxious on the subject of the coming election."
  - Jno. R. Thompson, Richmond, Virginia, to [James Barron] Hope,27 June 1856. (Box-folder 7A:7)
    Letter concerns a "Volume of Poems."
  - An undated list of officers, [1880]. (Box-folder 7A:8)
    Endorsement: "Part of list of Confed. Naval Officers. Keep."
  - Mrs. Marija F. C. Long, Quincy, Florida, to [James Barron] Hope,17 August 1883. (Box-folder 7A:9)
    Letter concerns an article in the paper about Janie Barron Hope, and statement "you was a great poet." Endorsement: "from 'Black Tinie."
  - W. O. Chandler, Atlanta, Georgia, to Mrs. Jennie Hope Marr, Lexington, Virginia, 5 April 1898. (Box-folder 7A:10)
    Letter concerns contribution of an article or story to the Alkahest Magazine.
  - Notes made by Janey Hope Marr on letters of her grandmother, Mrs. Jane A. Barron Hope, with typed transcript, [c. 1900]., 3 items. ADr. TDr. (Box-folder 7A:11)
    Letters of 1854-1857 written by Jane A. Barron Hope to Miss "Carrie" Campbell.
  - Evan R. Chesterman of Richmond Evening Journal, Richmond, Virginia, to Mrs. Robert Marr [Jane Barron Hope], Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Blacksburg, Virginia, and copy of reply, 29 November, 6 December 1908., 2 items. TLS. TCy. (Box-folder 7A:12)
    Request for information concerning the duels of James Barron Hope, one of which was fought at William and Mary College over membership in a literary society.
  - C. O. Paullin, Washington, D.C., to Mrs. Jane Barron Hope Marr, Blacksburg, Virginia, 18 January 1910. (Box-folder 7A:13)
    Letter concerns a manuscript account of the Barron-Decatur duel.
  - Col. Gordon McCabe, Richmond, Virginia, to Janey [Hope Marr],1 March 1910. (Box-folder 7A:14)
    Letter concerns article on naval history and the part played by the Barrons.
  - Lyon G. Tyler, Editor, William and Mary College, Quarterly Historical Magazine, Williamsburg, Virginia, to Mrs. Jane Hope Marr, Blacksburg, Virginia, 15 March 1910. (Box-folder 7A:15)
    Letter concerns information on the Barrons.
  - Notes on James Barron Hope, with typescript, April 1922., 17 items. ADr. TDr. CE. (Box-folder 7A:16)
    Autographed notes on James Barron Hope by his daughter [Jane Hope Marr] with typed copies of same and an additional typed note. The cover is endorsed, "Capt. Hope's sense of Humor, J[ane] H[ope] Marr."
  - Louis I. Jaffe of the Virginia Pilot and Norfolk Landmark, Norfolk, Virginia, to Mrs. Janey Hope Marr, Norfolk, Virginia, 1 July 1932., 2 items. TLS. PM. (Box-folder 7A:17)
    Letter concerns biographical sketch of James Barron Hope in The Dictionary of American Biography, with page from same.
  - Paul H. Hayne, Augusta, Georgia, to [?], n.d. (Box-folder 7A:18)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1873-1922., 32 items. N. E. (Box-folder 7A:19)
    Clipping concerning and by James Barron Hope, who was the founder and first editor of the Norfolk Landmark. Reviews of A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves, poems by his daughter Janey Hope Marr. Some are endorsed with comments.
  Series 7: Items collected by the daughter of James Barron Hope
- Items collected by the daughter of James Barron Hope, 1893-1905, n.d. (Box-folder 7B:1-24)
  Four letters, newspaper clippings, copies of periodicals and printed material collected by Janey Hope Marr, mainly concerned with her father, James Barron Hope.
  - S. S. Nottingham, Jr., Norfolk, Virginia, to Mrs. R. A. Marr, Lexington, Virginia, 25 February 1893. (Box-folder 7B:1)
    Letter concerns monument to James Barron Hope.
  - Announcement of an address by James Barron Hope, 27 April 1880. (Box-folder 7B:2)
  - Reprint of an ordinance for the establishment of the Virginia Navy, [1880]. (Box-folder 7B:3)
    Endorsement. Letter concerns Thomas Whiting and James Barron, the elder.
  - Membership certificate of Jane Hope in the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 25 December 1881. (Box-folder 7B:4)
  - Yorktown Centennial Celebration Announcement, 18 October 1881. (Box-folder 7B:5)
  - Printed resolutions of Stonewall Camp, Portsmouth, Confederate Veterans, 21 January 1885. (Box-folder 7B:6)
    Thanking Capt. James Barron Hope for reciting a poem.
  - Editorial of The Landmark by James Barron Hope, Editor, 23 July 1886. (Box-folder 7B:7)
    Letter concerns memorial to Lee.
  - Article from the Norfolk Landmark, 28 October 1887. (Box-folder 7B:8)
    Letter concerns laying cornerstone of Lee monument in Richmond.
  - Copy of Drake's Magazine, VIII:7, May 1890. (Box-folder 7B:9)
    Contains The Birthday of Joss by Janey Barron Hope Marr.
  - Hope Monument Ribbon, 10 May 1893. (Box-folder 7B:10)
  - Memorial ribbon for James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 7B:10)
  - Eight pages from notebooks with clippings, 1887. (Box-folder 7B:11)
    Letter concerns James Barron Hope, including memorial edition of The Norfolk Weekly Landmark for 21 September 1887. Includes ads, R. J. Bennett, Wadesboro, Auson County, North Carolina, to Mrs. James Barron Hope.
  - Editorial of The Richmond Dispatch with text of poem of the late James Barron Hope and address of Col. Charles Marshall at laying of cornerstone of Lee monument in Richmond, 4 November 1887. (Box-folder 7B:12)
  - 5 newspaper clippings concerning James Barron Hope, 1894-1899. (Box-folder 7B:13)
  - 7 newspaper clippings concerning James Barron Hope and his work, 1895. (Box-folder 7B:14)
  - Issue of The American Historical Register, No.8, April 1895. (Box-folder 7B:15)
    Includes an article on Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, by Janey Hope Marr.
  - The Messenger of Richmond College, XXII:5, March 1896. (Box-folder 7B:16)
    Includes an article on James Barron Hope.
  - The Conservative Review, III:1, March 1900. (Box-folder 7B:17)
    Contains an article on James Barron Hope by Janey Hope Marr.
  - Newspaper clippings concerning James Barron Hope, 1903-1932., 4 items. PN. (Box-folder 7B:18)
  - The William and Mary Literary Magazine, XVII:3, January 1908. (Box-folder 7B:19)
    Contains a poem by James Barron Hope and his photograph.
  - XI Hussar Journal, IV:2, April 1913. (Box-folder 7B:20)
    Includes poem Balaclava by James Barron Hope.
  - Photographs, endorsed on reverse, 1925., 6 items. Ph. E. (Box-folder 7B:21)
  - Printed notice, with endorsement by Janey Hope Marr, n.d. (Box-folder 7B:22)
  - Photograph of Wm. H. Polk, n.d. (Box-folder 7B:23)
    Endorsement by Mrs. Polk.
  - Photograph of the Yorktown Monument, n.d. (Box-folder 7B:24)
    Endorsement on reverse.
  Series 8: Miscellaneous Items
- Miscellaneous Items, 1861-1905, n.d. (Box-folder 8:1-27)
  - Written from Warrenton, North Carolina, 2 June 1861. (Box-folder 8:1)
    Note endorsed, "Written by Jane Barron Hope (Mrs. Wilton Hope) mother of Jas. Barron Hope."
  - Obituary of Mrs. Jane A. Hope, daughter of Comm. James Barron, 3 February 1862. (Box-folder 8:2)
  - J. B. Walters, Portsmouth, Virginia, to Capt. James Barron Hope, 28 March 1873. (Box-folder 8:3)
    Criticism of an editorial in The Virginian; endorsement by James Barron Hope concerns his reply. Endorsement by J[aney] B[arron] H[ope] M[arr] tells how this led to a near duel.
  - J. B. Walters to Capt. Jas. Barron Hope, 28 March 1873. (Box-folder 8:3)
    A demand for "satisfaction" sent by the hand of his friends Capt. B. Martin and F. J. Roche.
  - S. Barron, "Malvern," near Loretto, Essex County, Virginia, to Capt. J[ames] Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 27 August 1880. (Box-folder 8:4)
    Cover endorsed, "Uncle Sam Barron's letter about Lamb-Hope duel" signed J[aney] H[ope] Marr.
  - Editorial "The Code" which concerned the threatened duel between Col. Lamb and Capt. Hope, August 1880. (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Invitation to the Yorktown Centennial Celebration, 18 October 1881. (Box-folder 8:6)
  - A. S. Lloyd, Norfolk, to Jas. Barron Hope, Norfolk, 16 July 1887. (Box-folder 8:7)
    Sent with sketch of Pocahontas.
  - Jennie B. Marr, Warrenton, Virginia, to Mrs. Annie B. Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 18 September 1887. (Box-folder 8:8)
    Letter of condolence upon the death of Capt. [James Barron] Hope.
  - Edw'd R. Baird, "Epping Forrest," to Mrs. R. A. Marr, Norfolk, Virginia, 24 September 1887. (Box-folder 8:9)
    Letter of condolence upon the death of James [Barron Hope].
  - R. E. Lee, Jr., Washington, D.C., to Mrs. Marr, 13 December 1892. (Box-folder 8:10)
    Appreciation for a package of poems that he had received.
  - Article by Janey Hope Marr in the Hampton Monitor titled Correct Story of Hope-Lamb Affair,6 March 1903. (Box-folder 8:11)
  - Henry E. Shepherd, Baltimore, to Mrs. Janey Hope Marr, 13 June 1905. (Box-folder 8:12)
    Letter concerns his hearing of a recitation of a poem by [James Barron] Hope on August 8, 1866.
  - Announcement of the publication of Little Stories for Little People by James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 8:13)
  - Sketch, n.d. (Box-folder 8:14)
    Endorsed "Painted for my room...by my father, James Barron Hope." Signed Janey Hope Marr.
  - Printed notice of publication of A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves, selected poems of James Barron Hope, edited by his daughter, Janey Hope Marr, n.d. (Box-folder 8:15)
  - Anne V. Marr, "Notes to go with the Barron-Hope Papers," December 1965., 2 pages. TDS. (Box-folder 8:16)
    Explanation of museum items in Box VII; explanation of relationships of persons mentioned in letters; location of other Barron and other Hope items.
  - Items received on 7 December 1964, 1816, n.d. (Box-folder 8:17-21)
    Artifacts pertaining to James Barron Hope.
    - Silhouette of James Barron Hope, when 5 years old, n.d. (Box-folder 8:17)
    - Lace cap worn by James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 8:18)
    - Linen collar worn by James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 8:19)
    - Wedding slippers and stockings of Jane Barron Hope, married to Wilton Hope, 13 June 1816. (Box-folder 8:20)
    - Spectacles worn by James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 8:21)
  - Items presented by Miss Marr on 25 May 1965; 1816, n.d. (Box-folder 8:17-21)
    Portraits and artifacts pertaining to James Barron Hope.
    - Oval miniature of Elizabeth Barron French, daughter of James Barron the Younger, and wife of Dr. George French, n.d. (Box-folder 8:22)
      With attached colored drawing on tissue, representing her departed spirit, and illustrated with flowers, willow tree, gravestone, etc.
    - Small circular wooden box with note attached to base: "Relics of the olden times," 1825. (Box-folder 8:23)
      Note reads: "Relics of the olden times, A gift from J. F. Watson to Comdr Jas Barron. 1825. The box is of Walnut, a tree of Penn's day & the last left alive in the City of Philda. It stood till 1813 before the Hall of Independence. The oak on the lid is of the timber of the Alliance frigate, the last relic of the first Amn Navy. The Mahogany is of Columbus' house, the first in Amca, 1496."
      The following note is written on paper attached to the liner base of the box: "a characteristic of Presdt Harrison is very applicable to Comdre Barron, vizt: 'He has a remarkably suggestive mind; and having passed through a career full of incident & variety, his retentive memory seems to be constantly on the alert for illustrations drawn from his own experience of any points that may occur' --S. L. W."
    - Portrait (daguerreotype) of James Barron Hope, about 17 years of age, n.d. (Box-folder 8:24)
    - Copy of portrait (daguerreotype) of Commodore James Barron, the Younger, n.d. (Box-folder 8:25)
    - Portrait (daguerreotype) of Mrs. James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 8:26)
    - Portrait (photograph) tinted, of James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 8:27)
  Series 9: Various Issues of Newspapers
- Various Issues of Newspapers, 1854-1887. (Box-folder 9:1-5)
  - The Hampton News and Advertiser, August-September 1854., 5 issues. N. (Box-folder 9:1)
  - The Norfolk Landmark, 1 September 1886., 1 issue. N. (Box-folder 9:2)
    An extra issue pertaining to the earthquake in Charleston, South Carolina.
  - The Norfolk Landmark, 1877., 20 issues. N. (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Richmond Daily Whig, 1877., 1 issue. N. (Box-folder 9:4)
  - The Norfolk Landmark, 1880-1887., 7 complete issues and one clipping. N. (Box-folder 9:5)